Yseult Héjja-Brichard

Centre de Recherche Cerveau et Cognition CNRS - Université Paul Sabatier - UMR 5549 Pavillon Baudot - CHU Purpan - BP25202 31052 Toulouse Cedex 03 – France

> ✓ yseult.hejja@cnrs.fr • ♀ yseulthb.github.io • ✔ Izzie_Hb OSF: https://osf.io/nd82r/

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I recently completed my PhD studies in cognitive neuroscience and more specifically on depth perception in primate, with a link with natural statistics. For my next research projects, I aim to dive into the fields of sensory ecology and cognitive ecology to further investigate how sensory systems and cognitive functions of different species are shaped by or adapted to the environment in which they evolve.

EDUCATION

PhD studies in Neuroscience, Cognition, and Behaviour

2015 (Oct)- 2020 (June)

Université Paul Sabatier and CerCo (CNRS), Toulouse, France

Supervisor: Benoit R. Cottereau, within the Eco-3D team.

Title of the thesis: Spatial and temporal integration of binocular disparities in primates.

Msc in Neuroscience, Cognition, and Behaviour (2nd year)

2015

Université Paul Sabatier, Toulouse, France

Research project: "Characterisation of the cortical networks involved in 3D orientation processing in primates." at CerCo, Toulouse. Supervised by Benoit R. Cottereau & Jean-Baptiste Durand.

Msc in Cognitive and Social Psychology (1st year)

2014

Université de Grenoble-Alpes, Grenoble, France

Research project: "Role of the eyes in face categorisation: Interracial eye change impacts on the other-race effect in a categorisation task." at LPNC, Grenoble. Supervised by Olivier Pascalis. Internship in Neuropsychology at the Hospital of Grenoble, France (January-February 2014)

Bsc in Psychology 2013

Université de Grenoble-Alpes, France & Universität Leipzig, Germany

Research assistant at the Max Planck Institute for Human Cognitive and Brain Sciences, Leipzig, Germany - Department of social neuroscience (April-July 2013). Supervised by Natacha Mendes. *In charge of the coding of chimpanzees' vocalisations collected for an experiment investigating Schadenfreude.*

RESEARCH SKILLS

Computer tools

- *Programming:* Matlab, R, C#, Python (intermediate)
- o Neuroimaging: SPM12, caret5 (software for monkey data), PRoNTo (Pattern recognition toolbox)
- o *Stimulus presentation*: EventIDE (advanced), PsychToolbox, Eprime
- Writing: LaTeX, RMarkdown, Office
- o *Graphics editor:* Adobe Illustrator, Photoshop
- o Data and article sharing: Github, Open Science Framework, bioRxiv

Data analysis

- o fMRI data analyses (univariate, retinotopic, and multivariate pattern analyses)
- Psychophysical data modelling
- Eye-tracking analysis

SCIENTIFIC PRODUCTION

Publications

Under review or in preparation

- o Audurier, P., **Héjja-Brichard, Y.**, Kohler, P.J., Norcia, A.M., Durand, J.-B., Cottereau, B.R. (*in prep.*). Processing of symmetry in the non-human primate brain.
- De Castro, V., Smith, A.T., Beer, A.L., Leguen, C., Vayssière, N., Héjja-Brichard, Y., Audurier, P., Cottereau, B.R. & Durand, J.B. (*in revision*). Connectivity of the cingulate sulcus visual area (CSv) in macaque monkeys.

Peer-reviewed journal articles

- o Rima, S., Cottereau, B.R., **Héjja-Brichard, Y.**, Trotter, Y. & Durand, J.B. (2020). A new visuotopic cluster in macaque posterior parietal cortex revealed by wide-field retinotopy. *Brain Structure and Function*. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00429-020-02134-2
- Chauhan, T., Héjja-Brichard, Y., & Cottereau, B.R. (2020). Modelling binocular disparity processing from statistics in natural scenes. *Vision Research*, 176, 27-39. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.visres. 2020.07.009
- Héjja-Brichard, Y., Rima, S., Rapha, E., Durand, J.-B. & Cottereau, B.R. (2020). Stereomotion processing in the non-human primate brain. *Cerebral Cortex*, 30(8), 4528-4543. https://doi.org/10.1093/cercor/bhaa055. [Preprint & OSF project]
- Cottereau, B.R., Smith, A.T., Rima, S., Fize, D., Héjja-Brichard, Y., Renaud, L., ... & Durand, J.-B. (2017). Processing of Egomotion-Consistent Optic Flow in the Rhesus Macaque Cortex. Cerebral Cortex, 1-14. https://doi.org/10.1093/cercor/bhw412

Presentations

Invited talks

- o **Héjja-Brichard, Y.** & Mercier M.R. (2018). Data visualisation in cognitive neuroscience: Functional neuroimaging and electrophysiology. Toulouse Data Vizualisation group, Toulouse.
- o Héjja-Brichard, Y. (2018). Open Science: Why and How? CerCo's Young Scientist Meeting.

Conference talks

Audurier, P., Héjja-Brichard, Y., Kohler, P.J., Norcia, A.M., Durand, J.-B., Cottereau, B.R. (2019).
Processing of rotational symmetry in the non-human primate brain. Annual meeting of the French research group 'GDR Vision', Marseille, France.

Conference posters

- Audurier, P., Héjja-Brichard, Y., Kohler, P.J., Norcia, A.M., Durand, J.-B., Cottereau, B.R. (2019, October). Processing of symmetry in the non-human primate brain. Society for Neuroscience, Chicago, USA.
- o De Castro, V., LeGuen, C., **Héjja-Brichard, Y.**, Audurier, P., Cottereau, B.R., Durand, J.-B. (2019, October). Functional and structural connectivity of the cingulate sulcus visual (CSv) area in macaque monkeys. Society for Neuroscience, Chicago, USA.

- o **Héjja-Brichard, Y.**, Bruzzone, S.E.P., Rapha, E., Durand, J.-B., Cottereau, B.R. (2019, September). Influence of natural statistics on depth perception. Predictive Brain Conference, Marseille, France.
- Héjja-Brichard, Y., Rima, S., Rapha, E., Durand, J.-B., Cottereau, B.R. (2018, November). Stereomotion processing in the non-human primate brain. Society for Neuroscience, San Diego, USA.
- o Rima, S., Cottereau, B.R., **Héjja-Brichard, Y.**, Trotter, Y., Durand, J.-B. (2017, Nov.). Wide-field retinotopy reveals a new visuotopic cluster in IPS. Society for Neuroscience, Washington, USA.
- Héjja-Brichard, Y., Rima, S., Durand, J.-B., Cottereau, B.R. (2017, August). Stereomotion processing in the non-human primate brain. European Conference on Visual Perception, Berlin, Germany.
- **Héjja-Brichard, Y.**, Rima, S., Trotter, Y., Banks, M.S., Durand, J.-B., Cottereau, B.R. (2015, October). Adaptation to the 3D properties of the environment in non-human primates. GDR Vision annual forum, Grenoble, France.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Temporary teaching assistant (2019-2020) for Bsc Psychology students (1st year) - 48 hrs Department of Psychology, Université Toulouse Jean Jaurès, Toulouse, France.

Graduate teaching assistant (2015-2018) for Bsc Biology students (2nd and 3rd years) - 193 hrs Department of neuroscience and behavioural science, Université Paul Sabatier, Toulouse, France.

2019-2020

Introduction to Psychophysiology (PSYC, 1st year) TD: 48h

2017-2018

Nervous and cerebral functions (BCP, 3rd year) TD: 4h & TP: 33h

Behavioural ecology (BOPE, 3rd year) TP: 27h

2016-2017

Neurophysiology (BCP, 2nd year) TD: 4h

Nervous and cerebral functions (BCP, 3rd year) TD: 4h & TP: 36h

Behavioural ecology (BOPE, 3rd year) TP: 21h

2015-2016

Neuroscience (BCP, 2nd year) TP: 24h

Nervous and cerebral functions (BCP, 3rd year) TD: 6h & TP: 28h

Behavioural ecology (BOPE, 3rd year) TP: 6h

PSYC: Psychology; BCP: Cell Biology and Physiology; BOPE: Organisms, Populations, and Ecosystems Biology TD: tutorial classes; TP: practical works

Student supervision

- o 2019: Master's student in Neuroscience, Università degli studi di Trieste, Italy Psychophysics
- o 2018: Master's student in Neuroscience, University of Bordeaux, France fMRI analyses

EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

Lab Community Involvement

- o Organisation of the first edition of the Lab Student Day (2019)
- Co-creation of a Welcome Kit for new students and postdocs (2019)
- Student representative at the Lab Council (2017-2018)
- Organisation of the Lab Winter School (2017, 2018)

- o Ambassador for the Center for Open Science: COS (2018-present)
- Development of a collective with other young researchers to promote open and slow science

Personal Implication in Science Popularisation

- o Public presentation on visual illusions (March 2019) for the Brain Awareness Week in Toulouse.
- o Public presentation on the study of 3D vision in animals (February 2017), Museum de Toulouse.
- o Article for the Science Museum of Toulouse (2017, in French) about the evolution of 3D vision in animals: Y. Héjja-Brichard & B.R. Cottereau "Evolution et vision: le vivant a de la profondeur!"
- Communications manager and member of InCOGnu an organisation of students and young researchers in cognitive science in the Toulouse area. Organisation of monthly conferences, workshops for the general public and participation in various events of science popularisation.
- Member of FRESCO, a French organisation uniting at the national level all the regional organisations involved in popularising cognitive science. The FRESCO also has projects on its own. There, I am part of the Perspective team that aimed to create a new magazine targeting different audiences.

Complementary Skills and Training

- Languages French (native), English (full proficiency), German (good command in speaking, level B2), Spanish (basic communication skills, level B1).
- Methodological improvement Workshops in statistical analyses and in ethics
- o Certification Experimental research design in non-human primates, June 2016 (CNRS Marseille)